[Music]
good day good evening everybody and
welcome to the final episode of the ask
abijit show for this year ask abijit 225
I hope everybody is doing great so uh as
always I've taken a whole bunch of
questions that you have have asked in
the comments and I'm going to take as
many of these as I can over the next
couple of hours before that let's see
who all is there on the live chat I can
see anant Pai aasi Aro rudra Krishna
goind Alfred ragunath bul Ray from
Surinam from Sur M Netherlands anant Pai
once again VI sing galab DEA Lost Child
kapalin an shubam adikari prakar Gupta
enlightened Bing being Theos man Das
Gupta U XZ pray Paul from Kolkata Banda
Panda Nesh Patel goami geopolitical dub
hello malal B shash de Lost Child udb
Sharma xus Yus
zus Hedgehog's
dilemma uh DH hariharan by Yash
enlightened
being who else Sindra Desai jardan
s da vat Singh VI Singh arush Sinha uni
M aaya an Vishal Agarwal vardan Rana
Manoj Kakashi endan my cat's birthday
party feminist Slayer k mlin Mr Red Riot
om prash viit Jagdish Mali I am Kosik
dust of stars Kaya s Haring
bumar Panther quiet okay Mr 88 musan
choraria
buan pram
Agarwal kumal and so many other people
so welcome to you all thank you so much
for being on this final episode of asid
for this year and we're going to
continue next year so let's go and take
a look at the questions what questions
have you all asked me let's
see this is by balam Putin and sidar
Gupta raising your standards video when
also when is the bookstore and I am 20
and pursuing CA I respect you immensely
thank you and I'm inspired by your
saying never lower your standards but
recently I've realized that I have
actually lowered my standards greatly
how do I raise them okay so this is
something I keep saying isn't it raise
your standards keep raising your
standards so the question is how do you
raise your standards what do you what do
I mean by raise your standards what
standards are to be raised and so on now
this is not something I can explain over
two three minutes or over the the course
of one 15 minute video raising your
standards is a whole big deal I mean
it's about changing transforming
yourself
entirely it's it's it's got to do about
with it's got to do with mindset it's
got to do with your habits your routine
your objectives your goal your approach
your thought process all of that so it's
not possible to explain how to raise
your standards over one video so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to create a
whole series of videos starting the
first week of next year how to raise
your standards I think that's the way to
do it and we can go on a journey
together
about in raising our standards how about
that so that's what I'll do I'll create
a video a series of videos next year
starting next year starting next week
essentially raising how to raise your
standards that's what I'll do so yeah
hopefully that addresses that issue now
the book store will take somewhat longer
I mean yeah uh it's on my too list won't
happen very soon but I I haven't
forgotten it so thank you for the
reminder
right okay Vikram geopolitical says what
were the most significant geopolitical
moments of the Year according to you of
the Year
2024 hey look yeah that's a great
question a lot happened in 2024
geopolitically first of all the year
began with essentially a super cycle of
Elections right more than 60 70
countries held
elections and uh more than 4 billion
people were impacted by this I'm not
sure if 4 billion people participated
and actually cast their votes but they
were impacted by this the results
impacted their lives so some of the most
important elections were obviously the
Indian election in which Prime Minister
Modi secured a historic third term as
India's prime minister and that
obviously uh has helped us have
continuity in our policies internal and
external policies then you had the the
election in the United States the
presidential election in which Donald
Trump made a historic and dramatic
comeback and he won the president the
presidency despite all kinds of
controversies that have you know pursued
him ever since he became a politician
then there were parliamentary elections
in the EU the rise of the far right what
they call the far right and increasing
polarization essentially what uh the way
some media commentators like to put it
but you had that you had elections in
Taiwan which uh obviously have
significant implications for China and
the rest of the world so you had this
entire cycle of elections in 2024 that
has obviously had a geopolitical impact
and it's going to have a continuing
geopolitical impact now we can't discuss
geopolitics without discussing the
ongoing conflicts and the major conflict
two major conflicts one can think of one
is the uh ongoing Russia UK UK war and
Russian forces have been consolidating
their gains they have been gaining
ground there have been escalating
casualties on both sides we don't know
what the numbers are the numbers don't
come out they'll come out in history
books 20 30 years down the line but
right now we we don't know the numbers
so there's been all this going on the
Russia Ukraine war it's kind of
stalemate so to say right now it's in a
slow War Phase and yeah maybe it will be
resolved hopefully next year once Donald
Trump comes to power and things happen
if he wants those things to happen we
will see about that so uh that's the
Russia Ukraine war and there's weakening
support now for Ukraine I mean the world
kind of seems to have tired of this war
the media seems to have tired of it
various uh leaders and various Nations
seem to have tired of it and even the
United States seems to be kind of
looking for ways and means of getting
out of this war that's why I say that
maybe once Trump comes to power BRS
office things will change but now there
are fiscal limitations that are being
imposed on Ukraine and so on so the EU
also seems to be really wary of this war
so that's the Russia Ukraine war then
there have been tensions in the Middle
East obviously we know what happened
right the year before this year the
Hamas strike on terrorist attack on
Israel and then that has led to a war
the Israel Hamas conflict in Gaza so
that has intensified over the war
massive casualties and all that warnings
of uh humanitarian collapse humanitarian
crisis all that so that's an ongoing
thing uh then there's uh so this this
still has the potential of escalating
into a wider regional conflict obviously
the huis are involved hisbah is involved
from Lebanon Iran is involved there have
been strikes and counter strikes between
Israel and Iran as well so that's an
ongoing situation one of the major
conflicts uh one of the Sur surprising
things for some would have been the
overthrow of the Assad government Assad
regime so after years of Civil War which
started in the early 2010s uh Syrian
rebels they're called Rebels they
successfully toppled uh the government
of of President Bashar al- Assad and Mr
al-assad fled to Moscow with his family
which ended about five Decades of family
rule Assad family rule in the
country and this ISS going to this is
going to create a whole new situation a
whole new balance of power in the Middle
East in the West Asia region uh the
so-called Rebels who have who have won
after the Army inexplicably collapsed
these Rebels they are nothing but
rebranded Al-Qaeda Isis terrorists and
their leader Mr Mr Al julani himself is
a previously wanted terrorist with a
what $1 million or something bounty on
his head officially designated as a
terrorist by the us but now he puts on a
nice Blazer and everything changes so
he's now a proper world leader so
there's that and then obviously there's
the situation in Myanmar the Burmese
Civil War that's that's ongoing that's
going on and there is foreign
interference in the region which is
spilling over into India there is the
Manipur situation which is connected to
the Bangladesh to the to the Burma
situation the Burma Civil War there is
the US funded project K going on the the
project to create an artificial
Christian Nation out of parts of Burma
Manipur mizoram and Bangladesh that's
going
on uh so yeah there is that there has
been expansion of NATO this year Sweden
officially joined NATO became the 32nd
member of NATO and this was perhaps
uh a strategic response of the NATO
alliance to the evolving security
situation in Europe then there is there
has been a pact between Russia and North
Korea which is significant which is
interesting okay it's a notable
development so Russia and North Korea
signed a mutual defense uh agreement
which is a strategic agreement it's an
alliance and North Korean soldiers are
actually now deployed in Ukraine right
so that's something that has been
interesting you can see a whole uh
realignment of the global geopolitical
balance of power so we can see the of
what the West would call an axis the
Russia China Iran North Korea axis then
there have been various geopolitical
shifts one thing that hasn't really
shifted is China's assertiveness in the
South China Sea VAV Taiwan the Chinese
have been more aggressively uh asserting
their claims doing those U Naval
operations uh using various kinds of
Naval craft whether it's the Chinese
Navy or the uh Coast Guard or whatever
and this led led to several violent
confrontations in the region including
uh some situations that happened with
the
Philippines uh then uh the India China
relationship is some has seems to have
turned changed for the better so that's
a significant geopolitic de geopolitical
development for this year uh after a
nearly 5e border standoff uh the Nations
seem to have reached some kind of
agreement or understanding uh or some
kind of resolution Mutual resolution so
the standoff seems to have ended the
true positions have changed both have
withdrawn and Prime Minister Modi met
with President Shi Jinping for the first
time in several years and that's that
definitely signals better relations and
the and both the Nations have agreed to
revive bilateral di dialogue mechanisms
and there seems to be uh some kind of
pushed towards discussing the Border
issue and find trying to find ways of
resolving that now one cannot discuss
what happened geopolitically this year
without discussing the Bangladesh coup
so the democratically elected government
of shik Hina was overthrown by a
so-called students protest it was not
really the students protest that
overthrew her it was the army that
affected akou and gave her what 30
minutes 45 minutes to leave the country
so she had to flee to India and a puppet
government that is controlled by the the
US has come to power and the puppet the
figure head is Mr Mohammad
yunus and yeah so and this is a very
strongly anti-india government so
Bangladesh essentially has kind of
become East Pakistan again so what India
achieved in 1971 has been undone by the
Americans right so this is all part of
the American
uh repositioning of their of their power
projection in the subcontinent region um
economically the global economy remained
weak China's China seems to
have be be in the process of uh uh of an
economic downturn downturn and this
obviously will have Ripple effects
across the
world uh countries now are kind of not
really visibly in a panic mode but every
nation seems to be understanding that
you know you cannot remain completely
interconnected inde dependent with the
global economy interconnection is good
but you can't be dependent on other
nations for your vital needs so uh so
many major Powers most major powers are
now seeking to reduce Global
dependencies and they are seeking to
prioritize National Security over purely
economic considerations every major
nation is trying to figure out how to
create its own Supply chains that are
not dependent on others and so on so
that's something that's happening and
it's a consequence of uh the the entire
cycle that started with the Ukraine
War uh so there is that there is High
Cost of Living in various Nations and
this obviously has had outcomes econom
electorally uh various incumbents have
faced challenges various governments
that did come to power came to power
with with less numbers and so on so the
economy has really mattered and
obviously this is the age of AI the age
of drones the age of UFOs so that's
something that's going on uh and so on
and and the the EU the European Union
passed an artificial intelligence act
which uh is a legal framework for AI and
the objective is to regulate the
development and uh deployment of AI so
it's the world's first comprehensive
legal framework for AI and the EU has
passed that so we are now firmly in the
age of AI everything is AI enabled and
also the age of of Robotics in drones
and space exploration SpaceX has made
huge strides in space exploration so all
of this is kind of you could say the
highlights reel of this year
geopolitically okay Anonymous scientist
and Vikram geopolitical ask China has
recently unveiled its sixth generation
fighter jet which is absolutely
mindboggling not only this but they have
also revealed the wz9 div Eagle unmanned
stealth drone what should India do now
we are lagging behind what do you think
in how many years will we be able to
build Marvels like these China has
unveiled its six generation fighter jets
and what India has is the 4.5 generation
Rafal China did it before the US and
Russia what are your thoughts on this we
are still planning to launch the fifth
generation fighter jet of Our Own in
2035 will we ever be able to cover up
the gap between the defense capabilities
of China and India will the speed up
their launching of the sixth generation
fighter jets of their own sixth
generation fighter jets so first of
all um I would like to congratulate
China for this superb achievement I mean
it's not easy to do to achieve what
they've achieved they've done it before
the US I'm not sure if the US has a
working has a working prototype of f of
a sixth generation fighter jet maybe
they do maybe it's secret or whatever
but the Chinese have gone ahead and
revealed it it's they've actually flowed
it so a great achievement by China and
this is what happens when you put in
decades of incredibly hard work and
you're completely focused on your
National priorities so good job China I
would like to congratulate our Chinese
friends for what theyve achieved now
what about India what about the US what
about Russia I'm sure the US has a sixth
generation fighter jet program the
Russians also have it uh and sixth
generation fighter jets they have kind
of more better capabilities than fifth
generation fighter planes so more
stealth features more near space
features they can communicate
communicate with uh networks not just on
the Earth but also with satellites and
so much more futuristic weapons and uh
all that they will have robotic wingmen
aircraft they they'll have drones that
go with them and so much more so that's
the sixth generation fighter plane the
Chinese have done that the Americans
will definitely pursuing this whether we
know it or not whether it's re released
revealed or not and the same can be said
about Russia now when it comes to India
we are working on the fifth generation
amca Advanced medium combat aircraft
project uh like uh so like it's
mentioned over here U the first the the
it will it is scheduled to come into
operation sometime into in the mid
2030s and we are right now in the mid
2020 so a decade to go for that and only
then will we have a fifth generation
fighter plane the Chinese have two
different fifth generation fighter
planes the Americans have the uh
F35 uh and the Turks are working on a
fifth generation fighter plane and there
are various other nations that are doing
this the Russians have the sukko 57
which is a project that India was
involved in but for various reasons
India pulled out of it uh so India will
catch up with the fifth generation
technology sometime in the mid
2030s if things go well
and we can also start working certainly
in parallel on sixth generation of
fighter plane Technologies we certainly
can do that on the drawing board and uh
create scale small scale models and all
that but the main problem that India is
facing when it comes to fighter planes
is jet engine technology that's the
problem that India is facing and that's
an Achilles heel okay that's something
see the jet engine is what what powers
you plane you may have the best designs
in the world the best air frames and all
the stuff but if you don't have the jet
engine technology then you will forever
be dependent on somebody else and uh I
think we are buying the American General
Electric
f44 jet jet engine for the thees fighter
jet and the Americans are withholding
that right now as a means of squeezing
India arm twisting India so the entire
thees fighter plane project program can
essentially be shut down if the
Americans don't Supply this these uh jet
engines so that's the conundrum India
faces so I would say that India needs to
acquire jet engine technology acquire it
develop it buy beg borrow steal do
whatever it takes but get it
done the best solution is to pay whoever
is willing to sell it to you pay
whatever they're asking for just get the
technology get the ability to
manufacture the entire jet engine 100%
indigenously inhouse in India pay for it
if required I'm not sure why it takes so
long I mean there are countries that are
definitely willing to pay for technology
obviously they will charge you an arm
and a leg it's not going to be cheap but
it's not like India doesn't have
money right we have money for all kinds
of schemes freebie schemes and I don't
name them but you know what I mean we
have the money uh the question is will
somebody be willing to sell jet engine
technology there has been Talk of the
French safha getting involved and and
helping India with the c jet
engine so that's an option the Americans
will never sell you 100% of the
technology they'll always leave
something out the French May perhaps be
more amendable to selling 100% of engine
technology maybe not the best technology
that they have but maybe one generation
behind which is okay which is
fine uh so we should pursue that and
obviously then there is Russian
technology uh the sukko 30 fighter plane
the suo 35 also uses a Russian jet
engine called the Saturn al31 jet engine
and it's a pretty good engine uh and
even the Chinese uh planes like the J10
the j20 they also use the Saturn al31
engine so maybe we can talk to Russia
how much do you how much do you want us
to pay for a full transfer of technology
and it's not like we are Russia's
adversary of any kind so we are a
friendly Nation Oh I I am sure the
Russians will be willing to sell sell it
for a certain price or maybe maybe the
price is geopolitical we don't quite
know but we have to find a way of doing
this uh and obviously even if we acquire
even if we buy the full technology a
full transfer of Technology from one of
these nations we should still
continue uh developing the calary jet
engine completely indigenously obviously
we can use learnings from other programs
but we need to do that and the calary
engine no matter how long it takes we
need to make it work uh so the the
Chinese W whatever jet engine that they
use right now it has taken decades at
least 30 35 years they've been trying to
develop it there have been lots of
setbacks but they pers weird when it
comes to the calary jet engine we have
stopped it and started it multiple times
there have been times when the project
was abandoned and then it was restarted
after a few years that's sort of
nonsense jet engine technology takes
time to develop it's it's it takes a lot
of iterative improvements lots of
cumulative Lessons Learned From various
kinds of fields and what we need to do
is to invest in a Material Science
Program in India I cannot think of a
single Indian research institution that
has a m
um a worldclass Material Science Program
Material Science is developing exotic
and highly resilient materials materials
that can withstand temperature that will
melt
steel single uh Crystal Nickel Blades
and whatnot you know you need that sort
of technology to be able to develop the
components of the Jet Engine and to be
able to develop components that can
withstand incredibly high temperatures
and pressures for incredibly large
amount of time so that's a process that
takes years so we have to keep pers
persevering with this so uh we are
definitely far behind the Chinese and
even the fifth generation fighter planes
that Americans and whoever else Russians
have developed it uh the main Achilles
heel for us is the jet engine technology
we don't have it we need to find it
somehow acquire it somehow the Chinese
tried reverse engineering the Russian
jet engine but eventually through what
process they've been able to uh develop
their own jet engine technology I'm sure
it's not great yet but at least they
they're able to use their own jet
engines so that's the main issue that
India needs to address right now in the
coming let's say 5 10 years jet engine
technology in the meanwhile we should
also work on unmanned aircraft
technology we have a working cavy engine
that uh that can power power unmanned
aircraft drones the gatak Drone and and
so on uh dry tests are going to happen
soon in Russia we don't even have a test
bed test bed in which we can test jet
engines we don't even have that so I
think India needs to wake the hell up uh
I'm sure the future can be bright if the
right steps are taken so let's hope for
the best that's what that's what I can
say okay vicam geopolitical and kagam
Mar Rose K Kirk okay whatever that
is Pakistan is in talks with China to
get 40 fifth generation fighter playes
this will give Pakistan a huge Edge over
India China has parked 200 j20 fighter
planes on our border so by your logic or
as thin said qu quantity has a quality
of its own the government apparently is
still sleeping over the purchase of 114
fighter jets over the past two decades
okay uh so yes look China is a
geopolitical uh adversary of India right
now things may be going better uh the
relationship may be on a better track
right now uh because of mutual concerns
with much more powerful Nations and so
on but
uh geopolitically from the logic of
strategy China and India because of the
fact that they are two very powerful
Nations not equally powerful but quite
powerful Nations and they have a very
long Common shared border such Nations
can only be adversaries long term the
same goes to the same applies to Russia
and China so um China will definitely
want Pakistan to become a more powerful
nation that will obviously give them a
tremendous amount of Leverage in their
negotiations and dealings with India if
Pakistan becomes more powerful than what
it is right now and one of the ways of
doing it is to give is to supply
Pakistan fighter planes uh that are
superior to what India has so it may
happen Pakistan May acquire whatever
number it is 40 or whatever fifth
generation fighter planes from China and
that will give them a tremendous
Advantage because the Indian Air Force
is still mired in the 20th century
mindset of uh emphasizing dog fights and
and pilot skills over futuristic 21st
century
technology uh so yeah it will give if it
will definitely give Pakistan a very
large Advantage a very big and
significant and considerable advantage
over India
now it's not like we could not see this
coming this could have been seen coming
20 years ago even 10 years ago so what
have we been doing about it uh yeah the
purchase of 114 fighter jets I think the
government has decided to prioritize
building our own indigenous fighter
planes over purchasing 114 or whatever
number from abroad and as a stop Gap
measure we have purchased 36 refiles
from France so it's a small number it's
not a very large number it is quality
but definitely not quantity
so what should India do we need to
obviously ramp up the production of the
Tes fighter plane but you can't do that
when you don't have jet engines and we
are purchasing jet engines from the
Americans and they are withholding these
so we are in a very tight spot right
now uh as
a as a stop Gap measure or as a counter
measure one could perhaps modify the
thees fighter plane to uh be able to use
the Russian Saturn Al 31 or whatever
engine it's a different kind of engine
it's uh it's used in the sukai the Suk
has two of those engines so maybe we
could cut cut down our dependen on the
Americans and go for the Saturn engine
that the Russians have perhaps that
would definitely require modifying the
the airframe and whatever of the thees
but you know what at least the Russians
won't withhold uh fighter jet I mean the
jet engin from us so India needs to find
a solution to the tages issue and once
that Jet Engine Solution is found we
need to find ways of ramping up the
production right now what's the
production rate 12 per year 18 per year
I'm not sure what the rate is it's it's
not enough we need to double it at least
we can maybe create an second plant with
the same number of the same kind of
assembly line which can output the same
number as the existing plant so then we
can double the production rate of the
thees fighter plane and then over a few
years we can have significant numbers so
let's say Pakistan has 40 or 50 fifth
generation fighter planes and China has
whatever number let's say we have 300
cages fighter planes it then the quality
and quantity kind of offsets each other
and when it comes to Pakistan you don't
even need fighter planes actually drones
can do the job high quality unmanned AER
Vehicles you can Mass produce them and
use that to kind of blanket Pakistan in
in case of War you can hit whatever
number of targets you want with that and
drones are high are low visibility hard
to detect especially if they fly low and
you can send them in as many numbers as
you want then the Pakistan is in this
hypothetical scenario can shoot as many
missiles as they want expensive missiles
to bring the drones down but we just can
keep throwing more drones and that can
achieve whatever effect you want so you
don't need fighter planes when when
you're dealing with a nation that
doesn't have a large geographical
distance from India like Pakistan the
furthest point in Pakistan is just
couple of 100 kilometers from India
roughly give or take okay so Pakistan
can be easily dealt with using just
drones so I don't know if the Army Air
Force are thinking along these lines but
uh hopefully they are but this is the
21st century we can already see the way
the rules of the world the rules of
Warfare have completely Been Changed by
the introduction of these new
technologies so we should also do
that uh so Pakistan can be dealt with
using drones obviously if they send
fifth generation fighter planes into
India on an air strike then we need to
find ways of dealing with those and
obviously that's a that's a problem it's
a it's a technological problem it's a
military problem that the uh Armed
Forces need to solve so once again it
all comes down to fighter jet engines we
need to acquire jet engine technology
and we also need to need to very
seriously uh look at uh using various
ways of using drones and uh robotics in
Warfare
but at the end of the day we would also
want to have our fifth generation
fighter plane as soon as possible the
main problem is the jet engine once we
have that we can test fighter plane uh
designs and do whatever is required and
we need to very much take inspiration
from space X so uh when it comes to like
they have completely transformed the way
the space race is being looked at they
are the number one uh rocket
manufacturer in the world World whether
it's governments or private
organizations doesn't matter and they
are launching Rockets like there's no
tomorrow 100 plus launches every year
every week like two or three launches
and they have come such a long way just
2006 that they almost went bankrupt as a
company and their first two rocket
launches failed and finally the third
one succeeded that's how the company
remained viable but the technological
progress they've done over the past five
six years is incredible they have
developed Starship from almost scratch
if you look at the video of the first
test flight of Starship it doesn't even
look like a rocket that is that is 2018
or 2019 and see where they are today I
think it was 2019 that they first
launched Starship which looked like a
like a like a can and look at Starship
today they
have built up the technology they've
developed the technology so incredibly
fast so we can't be all bureaucratic and
slow paced when it comes to these
matters we have to do these things as
fast as possible so hopefully India
learns
from
SpaceX okay Mr 88 and vikor ask
questions about China and a dam China is
going to build China is going to build
the world's largest dam near India's
Border in Tibet it's obvious that India
can't do a thing against this decision
but this Dam does put the Northeast
states of India in grave danger of
possible flood scenarios what steps can
the government take to prevent such a
possible catastrophe also from a neutral
POV why is China even building the dam
in the first place it's is it one of the
ploys to keep India in check why are the
Chinese playing double games against
India by installing a dam on the
brahmaputra in Tibet on on the one hand
they are taking steps towards border DEC
deescalation and we thought there was
some tiny hope for improvement in in TI
ties after the 2020 Galvan clashes it
seemed due to the trade war and
increasing pressure from the US China
would inch closer to India and Bricks
would get stronger but as they say never
ever trust the Chinese even if their
economy stalls and they become weaker so
what's the deal what is the deal is the
question so uh yes the Chinese have
announced plans to build the world's
largest hydroelectric Dam on the
brahmaputra river in Tibet
there they call the river the yarong
Tango it's a Tibetan name uh so they're
planning to build a dam that is going to
produce three times as much
hydroelectricity as the Three Gorges Dam
which is also a Chinese Dam so that's
going to be a gigantic Dam it's going to
be on the
brahmaputra and obviously it's going to
have an effect
Downstream uh should we open the map we
can or should we okay let's take a look
at the map quickly let me remove this
from the screen let's go to Z map and
I'm not sure I'm not quite sure where
this Dam will be built it will be built
in Tibet we know that now the
brahmaputra river as you know it's a
very large river and it flows through
arunachal Pradesh and Assam and it goes
into Bangladesh where it merges with the
ganga and it's eventually called the
podma the podma river so this is the uh
the Brahma this is this is the coming
River where is the brahmaputra and where
does it come from and so on so on so
forth I think
uh so one thing we have to remember
maybe this is the brahmaputra is it yeah
this is the brahmaputra so it comes from
Tibet in Tibet it's a reasonably small
River but it becomes gigantic in India
so the first thing we have to understand
is that about 80% of the brahmaputra
water comes from within India most of it
comes from the rainfall that happens in
the Lush forests of arunachal Pradesh so
about 80% of the water of the
brahmaputra comes comes from within
India itself so even if the Chinese cut
off let's say hypothetically the flow of
water of the brahmaputra it will impact
only 20% of the flow 80% will still
continue as it is so uh from that
perspective we don't need to worry as
much
worry that much now secondly another
danger is that if the Chinese have
damned the river and then they suddenly
release a large quantity of water from
the dam then what can happen it can
definitely flood the downstream areas
and as we know Assam sees flooding every
single year very extensive flooding
happens every year in the rainy season
uh because of the flooding of of the
brahmaputra the brahmaputra is is prone
to flooding in the monsoons in in the
rainy season so this if the Chinese at
the same time that's flooding is
happening if they relase a large
quantity of water that can uh that that
can certainly worsen the
situation so these are the issues that
we are facing and we will face once the
Chinese build this Dam now the Chinese
have in the past held India Hostage to
such water issues I remember in the
early 2000s there was this buildup of an
artificial Lake in Tibet uh on a river
called the parichu or
something and uh there was a possibility
that this this artificial or Natural Dam
was it I don't know this Dam would burst
and it would flood very large parts of
India and cause all kinds of U damage so
this is something that Chinese have done
for a long time and if they build a dam
on the river brahmaputra in Tibet it can
certainly hold India hostage uh in this
manner so what are the Chinese up to is
the question why are they doing this
first of all we have to understand they
have the right to build any Dam they
want on their territory they they have
no agreement with India or any other
Nation about what kind of water usage
rights each country has and so on
there's no agreement of any kind so they
are well within the rights to build dams
on territory they control
right
um now what what has been the Chinese uh
response to these concerns let's find
out right so there is this article that
let's put on the screen and let's let's
read it briefly China defense plan to
build world's largest dam on the
brahmaputra river in Tibet the 137
billion project is being constructed in
the ecologically fragile Himalayan
region their foreign Ministry
spokesperson downplayed apprehensions on
the country's plan to build the world's
largest dam and they she said that the
mega project will not affect reparan
States and its safety concerns have been
addressed through Decades of studies so
she's essentially the Chinese
essentially says saying trust
us trust trust what we are saying
there'll be no effect there'll be no
impact uh that's not how the world works
right so the 30137 billion project is
being constructed in the ecologically
fragile Himalayan region located along a
tectonic plate boundary that can cause
earthquakes the region is tectonically
unstable we know that and she said that
the world's largest dam will not impact
low-lying areas she said China has
always been responsible blah blah blah
for the development of crossb rivers and
the hydr power development in Tibet has
been studied in an un in-depth way for
decades and Safeguard measures have been
taken for the security of the project
and ecological and Environmental
Protection SEC yeah so again trust me
bro is what what they are saying she add
the project will affect will not affect
lower reaches China will continue to
maintain communication with countries in
the lower reaches through existing
channels and set up cooperation on
disaster prevention and relief the
construction of the dam has been
approved it's going to be the planet's
biggest infrastructure project in Tibet
close to the Indian border it's going to
be built at a huge gorge in the
Himalayan reaches Where the brahmaputra
River makes a huge U-turn to flow into
arunachal Pradesh and then eventually
into
Bangladesh uh it will take at least a
decade to build it will re require
connecting to the grid further east is
there zero need Etc massive engineering
undertaking everyone Downstream is going
to be concerned about what it means if
water flow is reduced and India is very
anxious about it so the Chinese are
saying trust us we will not do you any
harm uh we are very trustworthy reliable
and we are very consistent with what we
do and so on so that's the situation
that's it's going to happen somewhere
north of arunachal Pradesh close to the
India
border and that's what that's the deal
uh so the question is what are the
Chinese doing uh as you can see vior is
saying that it looks like it looked like
India and China were going the right
track and China was making the Right
Moves towards de-escalating the tensions
with India but now they're doing this so
yeah that's how it that's how it goes
okay there's nothing you can do about it
the Chinese are well within the rights
to do what they are doing I'm not saying
it's it's the right thing to do it of
course is going to affect everybody else
it's going to give China a huge amount
of leverage on India and the downstream
Nations like
Bangladesh
and yeah so that's what happens when uh
another Nation controls the heights the
the high regions uh north of you the
downstream the Upstream regions so uh
it's a lesson that we should learn I
think in the centuries to come future
Indian geopolitical strategist should
understand that because of the mistakes
we made in the 20th century we are now
suffering from the consequences and we
are kind of in a position where we
are to be very Frank kind of helpless
against what the Chinese can do in the
future borders will change so future
geopolitical strategists Future Leaders
of India future Emperors of India should
take note of the
mistakes the previous generations have
made so right now there's nothing we can
do about it what we can do is
yeah so there's a chance of earthquakes
increasing and what India can do is
India can build multiple dams on the
brahmaputra in the arunachal Pradesh
Assam region that can you know
cumulatively taken together prevent any
Sudden Rush of
water from causing too much damage
that's that's going to be an engineering
challenge but I'm sure it can uh be
looked at that and probably the problem
can be solved so that's one thing India
could do to
mitigate
such an
eventuality okay this is uh big news
Hedgehog dma PR Paul and Sangita there
is an attack on Indians and Hindu
Americans online on the topic of H-1B
visas will this affect Trump's policy
towards India and immigration from India
PR says avoid amid discrimination
against Indian Hindus figures like Elon
Musk defend H1B visas prioritizing
Talent over nationalism does the US
agenda genuinely care for poor white
natives or is it slow solely about
Global Talent and power are oligarchs
like musk more about power than loyalty
to any land is this uniquely American or
a global Trend what are your thoughts on
racism on X especially after Elon Musk
backed the H1B program why Target only
Indians is it because we are not United
unlike other races who are and Indians
are among the most low abiding why isn't
the Indian government doing more to
address brain drain and improv domestic
conditions it's painful to watch so yes
the H1B Visa has become a hot issue of
very uh heated
debate and um what we are seeing is this
look Trump came to power on um on a
number of uh promises one of these
promises was to end illegal immigration
and Trump's voters are the conservatives
the
right-wingers uh the
Maga uh section of uh the US population
make America great again so they are the
conservatives they're the white
Christians mainly white people lots of
non-whites have also voted for Trump no
doubt about that but the main voter base
is the white Christians the conservative
uh section of the society
population
and they
are making a huge deal of the h1d Visa
they're saying that it takes away jobs
from white Americans from American
natives well natives is a wrong word to
use when it comes to white Americans but
okay American citizens and they said
that H1B Visa the H1B Visa scheme it uh
takes away jobs from the citizens and
gives them to Indians they are focusing
on Indians lots of Chinese come on H1B
visas but that's not being spoken
about um
now it's interesting that the annual
limit on the H1B Visa in the US is
65,000 and an additional 20,000 visas
are given to uh people people who
fulfill C certain criteria you need to
have master's degree or a higher degree
from a US educational institution so for
those there's an additional 20,000
uh a cap of 20,000 people so it's 65
plus 20 it's 85 so every year there is
this quota about 85,000 people can get
an H1B
visa and not all our Indians maybe not
even half our Indians so how many
Indians are actually coming in maybe 20
30,000 maybe at most
40,000 and these are highly skilled
people highly qualified people who come
and uh they they work for the US and
build the US and that's how the American
the nation has been built the US has
consistently had this policy of draining
the world of its St
and it it helps the US and destroys the
other countries right where the best
talent is immigrating
from um so that's the policy they've
always had but now these conservatives
they they are going after the Indians
they
are not seeing the fact that the Biden
Administration brought in millions of
lowquality low skilled illegal
immigrants into the
country instead of outraging about that
they are trying to pin the blame of
immigration on Indians so there is
definitely a racism angle in this
Indians unlike the Chinese I
mean Indians are definitely not United
as a as a single voting block so that's
why even the political parties don't
really care because
uh Indians are very uh individualistic
minded very Democratic minded and
Indians will vote about issues they they
and they don't Unite politically so if
in Canada for example the khalistanis
who are Canadian citizens they are all
United as a single voting block you do
something against them then they will
all vote against you in the next next
election it's guaranteed they vote as a
block in the US
Indians Hindus especially they don't
vote as a block they are they they are
always divided and that's why they they
don't really matter as a voting block so
it's
it's they are an easy punching bag they
are an easy scapegoat when it comes to
various situations the fact is that they
are contributing talent to India to to
the US they are building the US they as
we know it's it's the old cliche right
most of the uh most of the Fortune 500
CEOs not most but many of the Fortune
500 CEOs are Indian origin people when
it comes to whe it's whether it's
Microsoft SATA Nadel whether it is
alphabet Google Sund picai and whoever
else so many Indians are in charge of
these companies and they are well
helping the US cause right they're
working for their new their adopted
country um about 20 or 30% of NASA
employees are said to be Indians and so
on so Indians contribute a lot to the us
but they are the easiest Target the
easiest scapegoat and the H1B H1B Visa
issues is a very small issue just 65
,000 or 85,000 whichever way you want to
look at it per year it's no big deal and
these are high quality legal immigrants
not illegal immigrants so why aren't
they outraging about the illegals who
who are FL who have been flowing into
the US no no outrage about that now Elon
Musk has supported the H1B Visa program
as he would because he himself is an
immigrant he himself was born somewhere
else he and he became a naturalized US
citizen uh VI ramaswami has spoken about
this and he seem he seems to have taken
quite a meeting
online uh from the Maga crowd so yeah
there's all this happening right now
um so does the US agenda really care for
poor white natives or is it solely about
Global Talent power it's all about
Global Talent in power the US government
will always prioritize draining other
countries of
talent so that's going to continue will
all this affect Trump's policy towards
India and immigration from India you
know what it possibly could because at
the end of the day he has to do what his
voters uh prefer so it could perhaps
have some kind of impact on Trump's
policies once he comes into office Elon
Musk has definitely supported this thing
and he also along with with VI ramaswami
has taken quite a beating it all started
when Trump appointed somebody
to as as an in the role of the the AI
adviser to his government and this was
what sham Krishan I think an Indian
origin American so this is that's the
appointment that triggered everything
off so yeah Indians are most low abiding
Indians are the best qualified the
highest
earning ethnic group in the US and so on
but uh yeah easy targets what should
India do we
are being drained of our best talent
every year what should India do about
this it's well can fix a lot of things
we to fix the education system we have
to fix the country and make it
meritocratic we should respect Merit
instead of giving reservations to people
who don't deserve it people deserve who
deserve reservations deserve it only if
they are economically and financially
vulnerable uh but that's not being done
and uh ease of doing business needs to
improve so I'm sure the government is
working on these things but it will take
time hopefully hopefully should it
should take less time and India should
become the kind of country that is
attractive not just to its own citizens
but to Outsiders that's the kind of
country India needs to become in order
to be able to prevent and hopefully even
reverse the brain drain so yeah work in
progress hopefully work in progress uh
hopefully one sees signs and symptoms of
something being done about that still
early
days okay y naala says the US model of
immigration seems to attract most of the
elites of many countries including our
top rankers India let's say in the J
yeah how should we counter this since
this seems to give the US a permanent
Advantage if we open ourselves to this
sort of immigration immigration we would
encounter demographic change the US
seems to be encountering in its
territory over the past 70 years what's
the solution and is such an immigration
model sustainable in the US will all
immigrants
assimilate interesting question kind of
touched upon this in the previous
question but uh what's assimilation
first of all assimilation means you give
up your cult essentially assimilation
means you give up your culture and you
adopt the culture of your
adopted
Nation so if an IM Indian immigrant goes
to let's say France what does he mean
what does it mean for this person to
assimilate let's say an Indian family
moves to France what does it mean to say
that this this family has assimilated
into French society it means they they
speak French hopefully French at home uh
they they they they practice French
culture they support the French football
team and so on so forth you become fully
French you give up your culture and you
adopt your adopted country's culture
that is
assimilation
uh now you don't need to completely
assimilate in in in Multicultural
pluralistic Nations like the EU nations
in the western Nations it's okay to uh
to to practice your own religion to
speak your own language but you should
also at the same time speak the local
language as well hopefully as the
natives and you should work towards
acquiring that sort of fluency in the
language so there are certain things you
can do to assimilate and certain things
you don't need really need to do in the
US do all immigrants assimilate uh not
all assimilate but I definitely the
second generation immigr
assimilated which means the descendants
of the actual people who came into the
country from another country their
children definitely are much more
assimilated than the parents so that's
how it goes so now the US model of
immigration is a model of brain drain
you suck you suck out the best talent
from all countries especially large
Nations like India and China attract the
best talent now when it comes to China
the Chinese are very clear policy that
uh they are okay with Chinese students
going and studying in the US but they
have made China
increasingly
attractive for not just Chinese but for
the rest of the world and that's why
most Chinese students uh they eventually
go back to China or let's say they found
companies in the US and they start they
create startups or companies or whatever
uh but their allegiance to China doesn't
go away the Chinese typically
have Ways and Means of staying in
contact with Chinese citizens who settle
abroad so very few of these become US
citizens in the past lots of them did
become US citizens but now the trend
seems to be on a downward curve of
Chinese students becoming US citizens
acquiring US citizenship and even if
they acquire us citizenships they they
don't quite lose their uh ties with
China and allegiance to China the US is
very very aware of this phenomenon when
it comes to India there's no such
thing the moment out of India you want
to become a citizen of the other country
because there's nothing waiting for you
back in India that's historically being
the situation and even now India is not
in my opinion doing enough to make India
to make coming back to India an
attractive enough option for Indian
students who go
abroad long way to go for that so the US
takes advantage of this there's this
nation with tremendously gifted people
brilliant students the cream of the
population is brilliant I'm not saying
the whole population is geniuses
but India produces per capita more
Geniuses than other other countries
other other civilizations other cultures
so the US Taps into that the US is very
attractive and that's why they're able
to drain drain India um and obviously it
gives a permanent advantage to the US
right to the US um so what's the
solution the solution is to to make
India a top class country right now we
are classified as a third world country
not
unjustly there are are other terms used
for countries like India I'll not go
into that but we need to raise our
standards as a
nation there are countries that are
poorer than India with lower per capita
gdps that have better standards of
living it has a lot to do with the
corruption that is rampant allegedly in
India right uh so the government what
India needs to do is to is that the
government central government whoever
needs to launch a war on corruption but
that would mean that is
problematic for
politicians because of the nature of
politics in India launching a war on
corruption is problematic for any even
the tallest leaders
leaders because of the ground realities
of politics in India uh so but it has to
be done so uh if you address the issue
of corruption India will become a much
better country to live in uh the all the
infrastructure issues will quickly get
resolved or become go into the process
of being resolved
um and the quality of life standards of
living will will significantly improve
increase then we need to make India
meritocratic country no more
reservations or if you want to go give
reservations give reservations only to
those who are financially and
economically
vulnerable and reservations mean what
kind of reservations should be given
free education not free jobs not not
preference in jobs once you get your
free
education then you need to be the job
market just like everybody else else
without any special preference so that
needs to happen but that is nowhere near
happening in India and that's why people
who are from the general category they
want to leave India students children
kids youngsters why would they stay in a
country where where somebody who gets
way less marks then you will be given a
job but you won't get it why why would
you live there they will rightfully feel
that the country doesn't care about them
so they leave so these issues need to be
addressed the education system needs to
be reformed the ease of doing business
needs to be
reformed India needs to become a
manufacturing Hub a big much larger
economic power and if you do these
things there'll automatically be more
job creation there'll be a huge demand
for talent India needs to become an R&D
intensive Nation then you will attract
the best R&D Talent you know the best
researchers the best Engineers all of
these things need to happen uh we are
far away from that happening and so I so
that's what I can say that's what needs
to happen is it happening not quite
right now
okay P Paul and
viad why did Putin apologize to AER
Ban's president alev on the over the AAL
plane incident in Russian airspace
despite the external interference
reportedly caused by Ukrainian drone
attacks was this apology a gesture of
diplomacy an acknowledgement of Russia's
air defense response or part of a
broader strategic relations between
Russia and aeran what's the Rel reason
behind the crash of the aarani flight in
Kazakhstan as per aarani probe they are
blaming Russia for this can you explain
what's the perpetrator who is the
perpetrator behind this is I find hard
to believe that Russia would be involved
considering they have reasonably good
ties with aeran and Russia has strong
influence there as it was a former
Soviet Republic okay so a couple of days
ago uh few days ago this past week a
plane crashed in Kazakhstan uh shall we
go to the map let's go to the map and
find what happened where's the map let's
put that on the map
briefly so where where did this happen
it happened um so the so the aircraft
took
off not sure where it took off from
maybe from Baku and it was
going somewhere in Russia maybe gry or
somewhere I don't don't remember quite
where but it was supposed to go to its
destination and then it it made a detour
and went to AKA in Kazakhstan and
there's an airport outside of
akau where this aircraft sadly crash
landed it was not able to land on the
runway it crashed near the runway and
yeah that's what happened uh now if you
look at the video and
images if you look at the video and if
you look at the images of this crashed
plane and you we'll see that on the
fuselage on near the tail section around
the tail section there there are lots of
holes and those holes are caused by
shrapnel shrapnel is fragments fragments
of metal that come out of an exploding
bomb or device so
clearly this aircraft took a missile
strike it was struck by a missile an
anti-aircraft missile most likely and
how do this anti-aircraft missiles many
of these anti aircraft missiles work
many of these anti-aircraft missiles
they don't go and impact the plane head
on once they reach a certain distance
from the plane appr proximity fuse is
activated and the Warhead of the missile
detonates close to the plane but not it
doesn't impact the plane and when this
Warhead detonates it releases a very
large quantity of shrapnel pieces of
metal that riddle the plane with holes
and
severe and and these these pieces of
sharpel they severe the hydraulic lines
and whatnot so it makes the it makes the
plane impossible to control and operate
or difficult to operate and control and
it basically breaches the cabin the air
pressure drops and all kinds of terrible
things happen it can breach the fuel
tanks and drain the plane of fuel very
rapidly or cause a fire all sorts of
catastrophic things can happen so this
plane was hit by am that's that much is
clear and then it it went towards the
kazakhstani uh city of akau tried to
land there and the video shows the plane
struggling to to to land making 20 or3
turns trying to find a way of Landing
but clearly and and one of the survivors
said that what they heard a loud loud
bang outside the aircraft and after the
bang the plane started behaving like it
was drunk so it was not under control of
the pilots and eventually it crashed and
unfortunately several people have died
and hope thankfully some people survived
as
well now that's so that's what happened
that's the context now President Putin
has spoken with AER Ban's president
aliev and he has apologized in the
context of this plain crash Why would Mr
pin apologize so he has not
taken he has not taken the blame he has
not admitted that in so many words that
Russia shot the plane down but he has
apologized and he said that Russian air
defense systems were operational in the
area at this time
so the context the bigger context is
that at this time once you if you go
back to the map once
again at this time in this
region uh Ukraine it it is being claimed
by the
Russians that Ukrainian uh
drones were at that time hitting the
Russian cities of vladi kavkas grne and
maybe one or two more cities
so these are unmanned aial Vehicles uavs
drones pretty large drones that look
like cesna aircraft and similarly sized
or somewhat smaller in size and they can
drop bombs from the sky and they are
hard to detect and they and they don't
carry any any pilots and they were in
the process of uh attacking various
Russian cities civilian centers in the
region which is why Russian air defenses
were
operational and in comes an aircraft and
the Russian air defenses take it out so
it looks like that's what happened and
that's why it looks like Mr Putin
apologized to president aliev of aeran
without explicitly stating that Russia
is responsible for this plane crash so
that's what happens in
situations in in in Conflict zones in
war zones and which is why it makes
sense for civilian aircraft to stay away
from this region as far as possible the
Ukraine region and the
overall the surrounding
region uh we also a few years ago had a
Malaysian Airlines crash in this region
and that too was was shot down by uh a
surface to air missile and both sides
Ukraine as well as Russia have blamed
the other for that we don't quite know
who is behind it the West has blamed
Russia for
it okay Vikram geopolitical and gorov
ask Trump says he wants to control the
Panama Canal he wants the control back
in the US he wants to buy green line
from Denmark will he be successful in
doing this why does Trump want to make
literally every other North American
Nation as part of the
us uh Trump wants to Annex Canada he
calls Canada the 51st state of the US he
calls Justin trudo the governor of the
great state of Canada he has now sent a
proposal to Denmark for Greenland and he
plans to take over Panama the Panama
Canal what is Mr Trump thinking see Mr
Trump is a businessman first and
foremost his entire life he has been a
businessman and he thinks he sees the
world in in business terms so I think he
wants to make some Acquisitions for his
company for the United States and um so
what will the US gain let's say by by
acquiring Greenland by acquiring control
of the of the Panama Canal by taking
over Canada will it be a headache a net
positive net benefit for the US it
depends uh taking control of the of the
Panama Canal is obviously it's one of
the most important strategic choke
points in the world in case you don't
know where that is the Panama Canal
let's let's dive deep into it very
quickly uh it's this canal that that
connects the Atlantic Ocean to the
Pacific Ocean okay this is where it
exists and it's a pretty narrow canal
and before this canal was
built if you were in a ship and you want
to
uh travel from the Atlantic to the
Pacific or vice versa you had to go all
the way down south and you had to
navigate across Cape
Horn which is one of the most dread
dreaded passages in the world this is
paral Cabo de Hornos National Park Cape
Horn extremely rough Seas over here
extremely stormy weather in very very
perilous voyages if you want to navigate
the Cape of horn so the Panama Canal has
made life so much easier
and a tremendous amount of shipping
transits through that so if the US takes
control of it look Panama is an American
Nation as in as in it is part of the
Americas it's in Central America and
every nation in the Americas
is what's the V word the wasal world
right it's a vasal of the US they are
all controlled explicitly or Not by the
the US and they will not do anything
that goes against the interest of the US
and that's something the Americans have
striven to establish for a very long
time and they've established it long ago
more than a century ago the Monroe
Doctrine so uh so as it is the Panama
Canal is kind of under Us control
indirectly but let's say the Americans
take control of it then they will get
more direct control of it when it comes
to
Canada um the US spends a lot of money
every year sustaining Canada and and
giving all kinds of Aid and so on
looking after Canada's territorial
defense and whatnot so if the US takes
Canada over I think it'll be a net
benefit for both Nations the Canadians
will get a better government a better
system
maybe will they become the 51st state or
will like a whole bunch of new States be
added that that depends and that remains
to be seen But the Canadians will get a
better government a more effective
efficient government the and the US will
get a much larger territory I think it
could be a win-win for the US and Canada
for the people of Canada and the
US um Greenland is is rich in
resources uh natural resources so makes
sense for the US to acquire that and if
they really really want to acquire it
there's nothing Denmark can do to to
stop the Americans uh so president Trump
is thinking in terms of Acquisitions
he's thinking in terms of national
interest the only question is is this
going to be a net positive or negative I
think overall it's it could be a net
positive obviously the US bureaucrat and
Military will to expand and take over
these places and control places these
places and and set up the systems of
governance and all that it will take
some time it's going to cost some money
not small amounts of money but certainly
can be done the Americans know how to do
it so that's what is going on it'll be
an interesting four years when Mr Trump
is in
power Mr 88 says how can you call India
one of the four genuine Sovereign
Nations aside from Russia China and the
us when the matter of fact is that our
nation is still continuing the British
constitution the Judiciary System is
from the British times we see our
culture and people getting absorbed by
the Western propagandist on at will and
then we have our PM visiting Ukraine
from external pressure is having an
independent foreign policy the only
factor that should count when it toward
being called a genuinely Sovereign
Nation okay good question very good
question um I was recently in Hong Kong
a couple of weeks or so ago
um it was kind of a diplomatic visit so
to say uh and I had a conversation with
a Chinese professor of
law a conversation over coffee in a cafe
it we spoke for about an hour and I was
I wanted to understand the Chinese legal
system and the professor told me the
Chinese legal system it's it's got two
sets of laws one is for the criminal uh
criminal justice and one is for the uh
civilian Injustice let's say and the
Chinese legal system the Chinese legal
code is kind of copy pasted from various
European codes okay so it's not just
India that has British laws most
countries have have European and Western
laws they are the Chinese okay so the
judicial system is very much and and if
you go to maau Etc the judicial system
is in Portuguese maau is a part is a
part of China in in Hong Kong they have
a separate Judicial System compared to
China and so on so even in China you
have the situation okay uh the
Constitution the Chinese Constitution
I'm not sure I've not looked at it I am
not sure where it is taken from is it a
purely entirely Chinese civilization
Constitution or is it uh also inspired
by by various Western constitutions I'm
not sure uh but in India I agree the
Indian constitution is a copypaste job
of various Western constitutions the
judicial system is entirely rooted in uh
European jurist Prudence there's nothing
there are no Indian values or or there's
no Indian civilizational touch in the
Indian Judicial System the legal system
the laws all of that the Corpus of laws
that we have the penal codes and civil
codes and all that
um and so on
now why do I say that India is a
genuinely Sovereign Nation it's not just
about the independent foreign
policy uh overall the Indian government
and the overall the Indian
system it is aligned with the Indian
national interest not the Indian
civilizational interest but the Indian
national
interest and uh there is little or or
less foreign interference in this B you
can never never have zero foreign
interference even in the US even if
you're American uh but um overall we are
no one's
vasal so so number one we have um the
entire system is geared toward the
Indian national interest whether it is
the uh
government whether it is the military
important whether it is the way the kind
of laws you can pass and so on let me
contrast that with let's say Germany or
France or
Italy what does it mean for a nation to
be
Sovereign it means that your
democratically elected or
undemocratically elected whatever your
leadership should be able to pass its
own laws
right secondly they should it should be
able your nation should be able to
control its own currency and its own
economy yes in the EU
Nations can't even pass their own laws
their laws are essentially nothing but
rehashes of the laws that are passed in
Brussels the headquarters of the
European Union France or Germany or
Italy or Spain or whoever they aren't in
a position to pass laws that are
contradictory to what Brussels passes do
you call that sovereignty no it is not
sovereignty you are not a Sovereign
Nation anymore second secondly the the
currency in in the European Union is the
Euro the euro is essentially a rebranded
do
Mark okay so France had this great
currency the FRA the Frank gone wiped
out uh the Spanish had the the PESA the
peso what did they have probably the
peso gone wiped
out Italy had the L gone wiped out these
countries cannot even control their e
own economy they cannot even control a
currency that they own zero
sovereignty right so in the EU you have
pulled sovereignty the real power lies
in Brussels all the decision- making
happens in Brussels and these nations
are completely helpless then they don't
they can't even control their own
borders you have to allow in immigrants
the whole EU the shenen zone is open to
all citizens so you can't say okay
people from so so EU Nation cannot come
into my country because they are
troublemakers you can't say that anymore
you can't control your borders you can't
control your currency you can't control
your economy you can't even pass your
own
laws and if you are and if you happen to
be be a member of NATO even you don't
even control your own
military that is called lack of
sovereignty India has its own currency
India controls its own economy India
controls its own
borders there are problems but overall
we still control our borders so we have
our own currency
we have we control over economic the
entire economic activity we pass our own
laws we control our borders we can
decide who comes in who doesn't come
in and we don't have any foreign
military presence on Indian
Territory so if you put all of these
things together despite having
imperfections India is a genuinely
sovereign country and there are only
four such nations in the world the
US India
Russia and China No Other Nation is
fully
Sovereign okay there are other countries
you will give me examples okay so and so
country has its own currency so and so
country controls its own borders and so
on but these countries they will be
compromised in other ways their foreign
policy will be an extension of let's say
the US foreign policy let's say Japan
Japan has its
own uh currency the Yen which means that
they control their currency they control
their economy let's say let's say okay
uh they pass their own laws they have
elections they pass their own laws all
of that they control their
borders but then there's the question of
the US occupation of Japan more than 130
permanent US military bases on Japanese
soil and the the Japanese government
cannot take any big decisions when it
comes to military policy or security
policy or external policy or economy
without the approval of the US
generals and so on so there are so many
examples that you can give but I can
always give you counter points so there
are only four genuinely Sovereign
Nations the US Russia China and India
it's not only about the independent
foreign policy there's a whole lot more
that goes into this hopefully this makes
sense okay sarak says what are your
views on sending on India sending rise
to Bangladesh even after so much hatred
towards India
yeah India is sending uh selling rice to
Bangladesh look the Russians
sell high quality rocket engines to the
Americans the Rd something I forget the
the rocket engin name but the Americans
have been trying to replicate those
reverse Engineers those reverse engineer
those rocket engines it's not working so
the Russians are selling rocket engines
to the Americans even now I think soon
they'll stop selling them some kind of
announcement was made when the Americans
want to go to the International Space
Station they go on a Russian rocket the
soyuz rocket from bodor in Kazakhstan
the Russians have been selling all kinds
of stuff to the
Americans these two nations are
essentially at War but they still
engaging in trade they're being they're
being pragmatic they're being realistic
you can trade with your enemies you can
trade with those who hate you as long as
it's mutually beneficial as as long as
it it benefits
us so when it comes to India and
Bangladesh yeah we know that
unfortunately sadly tragically most
bangladeshis or many bangladeshis seem
to hate India it's not their fault first
understand that the hatred has a couple
of factors or reasons one is the
religious angle the Bangladeshi seem to
love
Pakistan o over
India despite what the pakistanis did to
their ancestors in
1971 we'll not go into those horrible
atrocities despite what the pakistanis
did to them the Bangladeshi many
bangladeshis Love
Pakistan and hate India you can't
explain that without looking into the
religious angle common religion right is
it their fault that they are born into
so and so religion or whatever it's not
their fault it's it's the consequences
of what happened in history the past
three four centuries
right there is that and then there's the
education system in Bangladesh which
teaches them them that Bangladesh won
its independence on its own the MTI
bahini fought the pakistanis and
defeated the pakistanis and only the
11th Hour the Indian army came in the
mukti bahini was
a okay let's not go into that we all
know what really happened here in India
but that's what the Bangladeshi
education system teaches them it's not
their fault they feel this way and then
the political climate is such that
everything is blamed on India the larger
neighbor
so that's why they hate India many of
them I would not say all but there are
many sensible bangladeshis too I'm
pretty sure I'm I'm I'm sure we have a
few viewers whom I've have interacted
with through comments and so it's not
all but now the fact is that Bangladesh
has undergone a coup shik Kaz has been
out overthrown a US backed puet regime
is in power Muhammad yunus is the
figurehead and the Army is actually
running the
show and Bangladesh's economy is doing
very poorly now it's going to do
increasingly more poorly it's going to
go on the same road as Pakistan now they
want rice so we are selling them rice we
are not giving it as a donation we
selling it to them not to sell rice to
Bangladesh would be childish and
Petty okay so as long as we are selling
rice to Bangladesh at the market rate
everything is fine as long as we are not
giving them rice on a discount there's
no need to give anybody a discount
everybody should purchase whatever the
want at market rate unless they are on
very good terms with us unless they are
a friendly na Nation so India and
Russia we are trading in oil and the
Russians have been offering India oil at
a discounted rate that happens when both
sides are
friends uh if Bangladesh wants to be our
friend we can certainly look after all
we are the same people we have the same
past the same ancestors but right now
we're in the situation so uh I am okay
with this
as long as we are selling rice to them
at the market rate at the correct rate
that's fine let's not be childish and
Petty okay we are all grown-ups aren't
we
hopefully Vikram geopolitical says
British publisher The Economist has
picked Bangladesh as the country of the
year what are my views on this how big
of a joke is it so when you when Time
Magazine nomin put somebody forth as the
person of the year it's a great honor
okay uh
it's it's one of the greatest
achievements an individual can have in
their life to be nomin to be uh chosen
as times person of the year now The
Economist has picked Bangladesh as the
nation of the year the country of the
year uh what has typically to be chosen
as a person of the year of the year you
need to be a person of great stature a
person of great substance and you need
to have achieved achieved
something very very massive that year
that's when you are uh given the title
of the person of the year by Time
Magazine similarly the same set of
criteria should apply to the nation of
the year the country of the year which
The Economist seems to
judge so the question is what great
achievement has Bangladesh done this
year is it a nation of great stature a
great nation of great substance
unfortunately it's not right we know
that is its economy doing magnificently
no it's going in the backward Direction
so why have they picked Bangladesh as
the country of the year it's it's it's a
pat on the back to Mr Muhammad yunus who
has in the past been given a Nobel Prize
as a pat on the back for his services to
the American cause and um so he has been
placed as the puppet prime minister or
puppet leader of Bangladesh sh has been
has been outed and just to uh
reintegrate Bangladesh into the
community of American vasal they have
given them this nice title of country of
the year I mean no disrespect to
Bangladesh or the Bangladeshi people but
that's just this is just a fact okay so
uh that's why they've done
it okay this is a very large question or
maybe a comment it's by Adrian I from
the EU and many things can be said about
what I have said about immigration your
theory that that immigration happens to
that immigration is being used as a tool
to make Europe harmless is just a theory
so he's disagreeing with my contention
that illegal immigration is being used
to reconfigure the demography of Europe
and to harm Europe he disagrees with
this so here's what he says I can think
of many things off the top of my hat hat
first of all Europe colonized other
parts of the world that is correct
people from former colonies naturally
came to Europe because they were
officially part of the country okay not
disagreement there that's why in the
Netherlands there are hindustani Dutch
from the former Dutch Colony Surinam yes
there are Black Dutch former slaves like
in the US there are Indonesian Dutch and
in France you have Algerian origin FR
French people and and morian origin
French people and so much
more um Europeans were used to
immigration immigration and immigration
to and from other parts of the world no
disagreement there from the 1960s and
70s onwards people from the
Mediterranean countries including Spain
Greece and Italy but also turkey and
Morocco came to so-call to came to do
so-called fil the labor that native
Dutch didn't want to do that's because
of the uh of the uh differential that
you have in the income levels of both
countries so when you have a high income
Nation like the Dutch where you have
very good living standards and you can
get a great quality of life even by
doing very manual labor or whatever
people would want to go to the country
why do so many Indians want to go to
Canada and become truck drivers or taxi
drivers because even doing that you have
a better quality of life than currently
have in India so yeah what you say makes
sense so people from these poorer
European countries like Spain Greece
Italy turkey Morocco and so on they came
to do uh less desirable work that the
Dutch citizens didn't want to do and
this is still happening people from
Eastern Europe like Poland are doing
work that native Dutch aren't doing fine
and these workers were simply allowed to
stay in the country all right they also
brought elements of their culture like
nice food it has all kinds of benefits
like it stimulates openness of mind and
tolerance to differences it reduces
racism xenophobia all that is fine
perfectly fine no question about it
still happens and it's wonderful when
you have people from wonderful countries
and wonderful cultures coming in and
they bring nice food and nice manners
and and exposure to all the to different
cultures it it it's great it's it's
stimulating to have an environment you
have where you have so many viewpoints
and so many uh other
things so I don't disagree with you at
all so what's my point what was my
original point my point was was not
about legal migration it was about
illegal migration my friend legal
migration is fine you follow the rules
and you come through due process and you
come into the country as a legal
immigrant and you are a law-abiding
member of society you respect the local
culture local Ro laws and you can also
uh maintain to follow your own continue
to follow your own customs and all that
and you are a law-abiding person that's
a legal immigrant what's a what's an
illegal immigrant an illegal immigrant
is by definition a criminal a person who
enters your country
illegally okay by by bypassing the newe
process the legal process the correct
immigration process the moment they are
in your country they are a criminal
because they've broken the law by coming
into your country and this is being
engineered right now in Europe people
are being shipped booted into Europe
across the Mediterranean Sea from
various parts of the world and these are
typically Young military age men without
any women or children with them and they
don't speak the language of the
countries they often don't speak the
language of the country they they're
entering and they come from a cultural
background that is very very different
from your cultural background they don't
respect your culture they they don't
respect your Traditions your culture
your way of life they want to impose
their way of life on you they are
violent they steal they break they
attack they harm
in very horrible
ways is is that something that uh
stimulates openness of mind and
tolerance of differences does that
reduce racism and xenophobia I think it
will actually cause more racism and
xenophobia in your countries my issue is
I mean I don't have a horse in this race
I don't have a dog in this fight it's
not my country I'm talking about I'm
talking about Europe my point is if
Europe continues this policy of allowing
illegal
immigrants military age males from
certain
cultures to come keep coming into Europe
in very large numbers soon of sooner or
later sooner more than later you're
going to lose your own
lands right that's my
point mcloven says how does deportation
work what if East Pakistan refuses to
take back their citizens deportation
what is deportation Deport ation is when
a country forcibly sends back a visitor
to their home country whether it's uh an
immigrant or a tourist or somebody who
has come for business or whatever but if
that person is
forcibly compelled to leave the country
that is called deportation so
deportation can be done at the
offender's own expense or if the
offender is not able to pay for it then
the then the host country will put that
person on a flight pay for the flight
and as the person and have the person
leave the country that's called
deportation you are expelled because you
are undesirable because you must have
committed some crime or something that's
generally why you are
deported so that's deportation now mavin
asks what if East Pakistan refuses to
take back their citizens so the issue
he's referring to is that of the illegal
Bangladeshi immigrants who have settled
in India maybe 100 million at least a 50
at least 50 million probably 100 million
that's a huge huge huge huge huge issue
for India huge national security issue
huge demographic issue huge issue of
every every single kind of that we're
facing in India
and one is assuming that when Trump
starts deporting the illegal immigrants
who Biden brought in that would give
India a great opportunity to to expel
and Deport all the illegal bangladeshis
out of India for that to happen you
would have to first identify
them all of them and put them in in in a
certain
containment camps before they are
deported right remove them from the
general population because they're
criminals they've come into India
illegally and they are illegally holding
fake frent Indian documents which they
have obtained illegally right that's
what happens when you are an illegal
immigrant who is squatting on Indian
Territory so that process will have to
happen before we can Deport anyone we
have to first identify each and every
one of them maybe 50 100 million that's
a very large number which means this
identification exercise is going to be a
very large exercise then you have to
physically remove them from the general
population so that they cannot do any
more harm and you to put them in
specially designated places as for as
little time as possible and then you can
Deport them through whatever means to
their home country through by Train by
bus by plane whatever yeah maybe we can
use military planes or whatever the
government can figure it out I'm not
sure this process has started yet but
let's say we start the process and we
are we have decided to deport the
Bangladesh's what happens if East
Pakistan which is Bangladesh refuses to
take back their back their
citizens yeah so um in that case India
has to ensure that whether they refuse
or not they will take it take these
people back and I'm sure we can use
various means to compel them to bring to
take these people back these people are
not our problem they are Bangladesh's
they need to go back to Bangladesh they
and their Descendants the obviously they
would have reproduced in India and their
children would have been born in India
but that doesn't mean a thing we don't
have you solely we have us of whatever
else uh we don't have ju sanguin we have
us sanguin is not Ju Sol so if you're
born on Indian Territory it doesn't
automatically make you an Indian citizen
uh only if your ancestors were Indian
your parents were grandparents or
whatever I'm not sure how it works but
something like that so uh if Bangladesh
refuses to take back the illegal
Bangladesh from India that India would
have to resort to some kind of force in
some way and that is something we can
easily
do uh so I think that once Trump comes
to power and he starts the process of
deporting the several million illegals
that b and Harris brought into the
country that would be a great opportune
time for India to deport the
bangladeshis who are squatting on Indian
Territory and
and I think it's an opportunity that
Prime Minister Modi should not
miss that's all I can
say Okay Sonia and Sunil say the US
government has stated that they don't
know for sure what these drones orbs or
plasmoids are but yet they are not
harmful to American citizens what logic
is this what isn't this a weird
statement and exus defense official said
we are not alone about us about UFO
sightings a while ago an Israeli space
security Chief said that aliens exist
and Trump knows about it what's the fact
here okay what's the fact here I don't
know I am not privy to any classified
information I can only make my judgments
and my statements based on what's
available what information is a
available in the public domain so I
don't know what the fact is here are
aliens really here sever several people
seem to be claiming that aliens are here
including very highly placed people and
yet without actual hard evidence I can't
say a thing about that so I I would
still say that it's still here say we
still don't have any hard evidence
there's no question about the fact that
there is hard evidence of these objects
in the sky whether they are orbs or
plasmoids or drone like things or
whatever these UFOs do exist they're all
over the place in the
US but what's funny is this you want to
hear the funny
thing the funny thing is that see the
past few
weeks these UFOs uaps whatever you want
to call them they have been flying over
New Jersey multiple sightings every
night lots of them at the same time in
the sky like multiple UFOs in the sky at
the same time like 5 10 15 20 they were
even caught caught live broadcast live
during a news broadcast not in New
Jersey somewhere else but yeah there was
this shot of the night sky with City
Line sky line of the city and in the sky
you could see these
weird objects moving around it came live
in a news broadcast so there's no
question anymore about the fact that
these things exist now the funny thing
is
this on December 25 there
was probably no UFO activity over New
Jersey it's Christmas
day so what does that tell us
are these
aliens
Christian or are these are these objects
operated by Christians it's kind of
interesting right that on Christmas Day
the drones disappeared or the UFOs
disappeared yeah so that perhaps gives
us a clue as to what the true nature and
origin of this phenomenon is maybe it's
not aliens maybe it is secret US
military technology that is being
uh deployed for to whatever end we don't
know what the end is but looks like
that yal kiss says how does a government
deal with moles or Spies of foreign
powers in its highest positions like the
polit bureau or in the cabinet is it
possible to guard against such moles or
is it a matter of
luck okay we'll take the first question
first how does a government deal with
traitors moles MO is a person who is
embedded in your country in your
government apparatus and who is working
to towards serving the interests of an
enemy Nation or another nation and at
the same time he or she is compromising
your National
Security that's that's a mole it's a spy
it's a
traitor now ask yourselves with this
very simple question during the days of
the great Chandra gupt Maia and
vishnugupt chanakya
what was the punishment for high treason
high treason means treason against the
nation against the
civilization very simple answer death
penalty if you betray your nation the
only punishment is death that's what we
had historically not just during the
time of CH chanakya and vishnugupt and
Chandra gup Maia but
always many things can be can be
forgiven many transgressions can be
forgiven or or given lenient punishments
but if you betray your nation there's
only one punishment historically it has
always been that not just in Barat not
just in India it's been the same
everywhere and in the UK in England they
had even worse punishment than death it
was called hanging drawing and
quartering have you watched the movie
Brave
heart well the final sequence in Brave
heart is an example of somebody being
hanged drawn and quartered that's what
they did to William Wallace I have been
there I have been to the Tower of London
I've held the spike on which his head
was eventually kept anyway that's a I'm
digressing the historically the
punishment for treason high treason has
been death that's what governments
historically did but today we have all
kinds of laws and stuff so I don't know
but the question the question is okay
forget about what punishment you give
maybe you give them life imprisonment or
whatever but how
can you guard against such moles can you
guard against
traitors so let's take the example of
China since around 2010 the Chinese
systematically identified every single
traitor who was embedded in the Chinese
Communist party and who was working for
the United
States and each of these traitors was
identified
apprehended and uh neutralized let's
say every single one of
them and that's how the US lost its hold
on China and that's how China has become
a completely genuinely completely
Sovereign Nation now look spies exist in
every nation every nation has spies
embedded within and India is not some
special case Indians like to Indians
have this very defeatist mindset that
India Indian culture and Indian people
are the most treasonous people in the
world we have more traitors than anybody
else in the world no it's not the case
have you heard of the year of the spy in
the US
uh okay I'll not put that on on the
screen but Google the year of the spy
and how many spies were exposed in the
US in just one year very high-profile
spies spying on behalf of the
USSR and the same thing happened in the
UK lots of American spies were caught in
Russia and so on in the USSR spies exist
everywhere there's always a certain
percentage of of your population that is
going to have these anti-national uh
criminal and and and treasonous
tendencies a small small percentage of
any population has this so those are
identified with by foreign powers and
then they are utilized in this matter so
what do you do to guard against moles
you develop your counter
Espionage
capabilities during the time of Chandra
Gupta morya vishnugupta chanakya there
were spies everywhere the Empire had
spies
everywhere I'm not saying you need to
become a police state and you need to
have spies every there but yeah if you
take your survival seriously if you take
uh your role as a great nation seriously
you need to have these capabilities
surveillance capabilities and you need
to know who can be compromised who
cannot be compromised and there are
certain signs and symptoms of a person
who is more likely to be compromised and
I will not go into that because it is
problematic
um
look it's easier to compromise somebody
in government in power who has children
who was who are living in a foreign
country just a fact of life it's easier
to compromise somebody who's married to
a person of foreign origin and so on and
so forth so uh I'm just saying I'm not
pointing fingers at anybody I'm not
naming anybody I'm just saying typically
historically
generally in a theoretical manner that's
that's how you know who to keep an eye
on and generally such people should not
even be be in positions of
power uh but today the world is a
different place for for a certain period
of time it will eventually revert to the
old ways maybe in a different way but
the old ways
yeah okay Sun Moon says why is Christmas
celebrated all over bhat when the
population is less than 10% is this a
marketing plan I
think officially the population of
Christians in India is less than 2 or 3%
they claim that they are the one of the
smallest minorities in India actually on
the ground the population may be in in
excess of 10% because of all the
conversions that have been happening on
an industrial scale but they don't
advertise it so officially technically
the population is less than 2 or 3% in
India and yet we celebrate Christmas all
over the year first of all it all
started by the government declaring
Christmas as a holiday and giving
everybody a Christmas vacation this
started in 1947 at which time India's
population of Christians would have been
less than 1% I'm
sure
right why did India have to slavishly
follow the Western ways why do we have a
Christmas vacation in
Winter doesn't make sense our summer
vacation the two two month holiday that
students get that should be in Winter
and you should have holidays for Diwali
and the Indian festivals but we have a
vacation for Christmas Even though no
one celebrates Christmas no one used to
celebrate Christmas and so Christmas
obviously is a
holiday and then in the armed forces you
have this great Christmas tradition you
know Christmas is a great event in the
armed forces because India's Armed
Forces uh have this colonial Legacy and
today there's so much marketing around
Christmas that everybody in India
celebrates Christmas Happy Christmas
Merry Christmas two non-christians two
Hindus will will greet each other happy
Christmas Merry
Christmas I mean I have nothing against
Christmas I have against nothing against
that religion it's just not our religion
civilization and there are efforts being
made right now to
to demographically
re-engineer India there are massive
amounts of funds being poured into
conversions of Indians into Christianity
you can see what's happening in Punjab
you can see what's happening in every
tribal belt these people these
individuals missionaries that come in on
tourist visas indulge in missionary
activity and now there are there are all
these homegrown missionaries who are
doing the same work this is a national
security threat it's a civilizational
threat I have nothing against any
individual voluntarily deciding to
become Christian it's your choice live
your life your choice entirely but this
industrial scale demographic
re-engineering project is a national and
civilizational security
threat and now because of the media the
entertainment industry everybody in
India celebrates Christmas it's becoming
slowly bigger than Diwali right the
government clamps down on Diwali cracks
on Diwali you can't Pro you know you
can't burst firecrackers they are bad
for the environment they they scare dogs
and birds so firecrackers are bad if you
and and the Supreme Court goes after
that the government of India goes after
the state governments goes go after
Diwali so Diwali is becoming every year
slowly muted down it's it's dying soon
it will be a very quiet subdued Festival
in just a few years by the end of the
decade it'll be almost quiet silent but
you can do crackers to your heart's
content on CH was a new year right
nobody's going to say a word about that
no government will will speak up in that
case the media the entertainment
industry everybody is doing this so
Christmas is becoming a really big deal
and the problem is if you say something
to youngsters like don't do this they're
going to want to do it even more I
remember when I was in college
University and all that uh there were
these organizations that that used to uh
protest against Valentine's Day and I
was of the opinion at the time that why
are they doing this let people do
whatever they want mind your business so
today I am older
invisor that's a foreign import we don't
need that we have our own way of
celebrating love uh but you know this is
what's being done so this is all a
consequence of mental colonization it's
all a consequence of the
foreign um the foreign education system
that we have
the British colonial education system
that still continues today in in a
different 21st century Avatar is because
of the anti-hindu policies of the
government of India and the various
government branches of the government
Machinery India is the most is the
world's most Hindu phobic nation and as
a consequence people are looking at
other Rel other festivals like Christian
like Christmas and so on to celebrate
because nobody cracks down on that and
these festivals like Christmas are being
portrayed is really cool in the media
and the entertainment industry you have
MS doni putting up Santa Claus outfit
all the cool people they do Christmas so
all the kids also want to do it now in
Diwali and and Hindu festivals are
subtly portrayed as not cool not cool
you know so that
is what is happening in India
Sun Moon 0877 says why are birth rates
declining all over the world there are
multiple reasons for the decline of
birth rates all over the world um the
whole world is now following the Western
model the production consumption model
the capitalistic model in which uh and
and in which your time you you're paid
for your time so most people want a 9
to8 job or whatever or and in India when
you take a 9 to8 job it typically
becomes a 9 to12 job you know not 12
sorry 9 to5 right 9 to5 becomes 9 to8 or
9 to9 people usually work work over time
for the same amount of pay and so on uh
and because there are not enough high
quality jobs in India once you have a
job you will do whatever it takes to
stay to to retain that job um so people
are overworked more and more the people
are increasingly overworked look at the
situation in Japan extreme overwork
there look at the situation in Korea
South Korea extreme overwork and where
you have and and the cost of living is
very high the cost of raising child is
very high so most people because they
are so overworked they're so exhausted
they don't have the time to spend with
their spouses and even if they some have
some time to spend with the spouse they
simply can't afford to raise children or
even if they can afford to raise
children they are now living in nuclear
families away from their parents and the
extended family so there's no one to
take care of the child so because of
these factors birth rates are plummeting
all across the
world Imagine you you have a job right
next to your house you work for eight
hours or whatever you come back home and
you have the weekend off and you have a
lot of quality time that you can spend
at home with your family with your
spouse and so on you got to have
children but if you are constantly
stressed out if you're spending two
three hours a day traveling you're
working 8 12 hours a day you're working
weekends and there is this cash Crunch
and everything is expensive you're not
going to have children and that's the
situation you're seeing all across the
world and then there's the decline of
the family system not in India thus far
it's going to happen we going in that
direction but the decline of the family
system family system worldwide
especially in the west most people get
divorced in one or two years two three
years most kids live in single parent uh
house households usually single mother
households because the women generally
get to get custody of the child and so
on that also is causing a significant
decline um in society and so on so these
are these are the reasons why birth
rates are declining all across the world
and that is going to be a problem long
term
okay samrat Singh and Sonia what's your
opinion on Pakistan's recent attack on
innocent Afghan children and women also
why doesn't India secretly fund militant
groups in Pakistan and keep it
perpetually occupied with internal
issues allowing us to focus on our
growth and
development Taliban has attacked
Pakistan is it an allout war is an
allout War a possibility between the two
countries and what's the impact on India
yes so the Taliban and the pakistanis
are at it again the Pakistani Air Force
La so it all started with with action
that the pakistanis took the Pakistani
military Air Force whatever you want to
call it launched air strikes on Targets
in Afghanistan which ended up killing
civilians women children Etc so the
Taliban has retaliated and there's
firing and shelling and what not
happening across the border this is
something that's going to happen over
and over again it's been
happening repeatedly in the past ever
since the the Taliban took over took
took control of Afghanistan uh so what's
my opinion it's it's regrettable that
the Pakistani has killed children and
women very bad but that's Pakistan right
what what can you expect from them um is
an allout War a possibility between the
two Nations no allout war is difficult
it can't happen because of the Stark
power asymmetry between the two Nations
Pakistan has a very powerful military
compared to what Afghanistan has and
they were professional military compared
to what the
Afghan government has Taliban government
has the Taliban is not a professional
military they were guillas they know how
to fight and all but they don't know how
to fight as a professional Armed Force
which gives them some advantages but
also gives them
disadvantages and of course the
pakistanis have the kind of equipment
the Afghans don't have they have all
kinds of fighter planes um Chinese
origin fighter planes American f16s they
have missiles of various kinds they
don't even need to use nukes in the case
of Afghanistan it's reserved for India
so uh there's a huge power asymmetry
between Pakistan and Afghanistan and
that's why an allout War simply can't
happen Pakistan is going to occupy
Afghanistan tomorrow if they want of
course they will be made to bleed by the
Taliban Taliban will go back to fighting
their old gerilla tactics and Pakistan
will have a big handful on their hands
if they try to invade Afghanistan uh but
they can do that so allout war is not
really possible yeah uh why doesn't
India secretly fund milit militant
groups in Pakistan
look we are focusing on our growth and
development right now aren't we is
Pakistan able to hamper our growth and
development in any way
today they can't Pakistan
is not important anymore for India in
the 1980s and '90s and 2000s Pakistan
and India were kind of on par on the
same level now India has gone way ahead
of Pakistan there's nothing Pakistan can
do even if it
wants to uh impede our growth and
development so what we are doing is the
right thing we are ignoring Pakistan and
focusing on our growth and development
why doesn't India secretly fund militant
groups in Pakistan and so on look you
said the word secret right secretly fund
so let's say hypothetically if India is
secretly funding these groups would we
advertise it would you or me come to
know about it no these activities if
they are happening hypothetically then
they are supposed to be secret so that's
why we would not know about it that's
what I would say
now the last part is impact on India
Pakistan Afghanistan fighting again
impact on India minimal
minimal
okay okay Vikram geopolitical says I am
very much interested in cinema and have
good knowledge about it I want to write
in direct films how difficult is it to
break into the industry as an outsider
without any connections professional
film making equipment uh courses
provided by some colleges are out of my
budget what should I try what should I
study study in undergrad for it I will
complete the 12th standard this year is
it a wise decision to go for film making
as a career in India or should I go for
safer options please answer me I'm very
confused I'm I'm glad it's great to have
this ambition this aspiration to become
a filmmaker you want to write and direct
films that's great breaking into the
industry in India is very difficult
Bollywood is a closed club uh even
extremely talented people who did who
did kind of make it don't really succeed
in Bollywood because
of the alleged nepotism problem and all
that now if you set Bollywood aside and
look at other Industries I'm not sure
how it works the various film Industries
down south very big film Industries they
produce a lot of movies some of them are
really good as well then there is the
Bengali film industry the tolywood in
Kolkata there are lots of film
Industries in India each would have a
different process of of getting into it
now today the the point is that film
making has been democratized by advances
in technology you see
traditionally if you go back 20 years or
even 10 Years film making was a very
expensive sport let's say sport film
making was extremely expensive you
needed extremely expensive cameras you
needed to pay all the technicians who
would work on the camera you would need
to pay actors or if you making
documentary you need to get gain access
to locations get
permissions you need to carry the
equipment in vehicles
then once you make the once you film
everything you mean the film equipment
the the film was expensive the actual
film on which everything was stored was
expensive then after filming you needed
to know how to do the editing
editing was a whole different thing once
you do the editing and you have your
entire film finally made you needed to
release it into theaters and for that
you needed con connections and contacts
and whatnot it was such a difficult
process
today you just need a phone to make a
film movies have been made have been
shot on the
iPhone or you can so an iPhone is an
expensive thing so you can even get a
regular phone as long as it as it shoots
HD 1080p you can make a movie iPhones
can shoot uh what
4K so today the investment isn't that
much for
you can get a very
decent uh phone camera for maybe a few
few tens of thousands of rupees maybe 30
40 50,000 Rupees you'll get a very
decent phone camera that can capture
video at at very high quality maybe even
4K if you get an iPhone which which is
about I don't know roughly one lakh
depending on whatever the the
specifications you can have really
cinematic footage movies have been shot
on iPhones if you want to spend two
three lakhs
rupees then you can buy a Sony fx3 or
whatever A7 S3 plus a few lenses that's
going to set you back by maybe four five
lakhs once you have that you just need a
laptop high quality laptop 32GB RAM and
gaming laptop and whatever software you
want some free software is available for
editing once you have this equipment you
can make any movie you
want right so you don't need permission
today to become a filmmaker and you
don't need to do courses
the best course you can do is to take
your camera out there and start filming
every day start filming every day try
and emulate the style of your favorite
director if you don't have subjects that
is the actors try and film in public in
public if you're in public filming is
and taking photographs is perfectly
legal because it's a public space try
and get cinematics shots and whatnot and
try and tell a story or try try and
create a documentary or whatever or try
and makeing yourself try and making try
and make yourself the main focus of your
of your initial movies right Vlog style
movies so today you can do anything and
when it comes to distribution and
release initially release it on YouTube
some of the best directors started as
Indie directors independent directors
with very small budgets one of the
greatest directors of all time is
Quentin Tarantino he started as a very
small budget
filmmaker but eventually his style was
such that you know he made it big
today all you have to do is pursue the
craft don't go and waste money on film
making courses you can get all the
education you need of film making by by
just
watching the movies made by the greats
Akira
kuros felini Tarantino whoever whoever
you like study those movies don't watch
them as a consumer just being
entertained but study each each scene
each frame each shot the composition the
angle the lighting study all of
that okay and try and replicate that and
and just start just start this is the
easiest thing in the world start with a
phone
camera and uh make a movie every day
make a five minute movie every day make
a 10-minute movie day every day that's
the kind of education you need as a
filmmaker acquire the skills hone your
craft that's what you need to do uh and
release it all on YouTube if you have
quality I mean initially the quality
want be there but after you make 10 20
30 50 100 short films like this the
quality will come if you have the talent
it will be visible and then people will
take
notice because it's on YouTube and
YouTube is democratic anybody can get
notice can get noticed and then if the
quality is there you can actually get
funding and you can start making high
quality big budget Productions so that's
what you do that's how you do it all the
best my friend don't give up in your
dreams go get your education but also
pursue this this this dream of
yours and uh yeah I wish you all the
best do
well uh okay this question here by
Krishna runat
surinamese um the question is how long
will the internet last and what could
possibly replace the
internet that's an interesting question
people generally don't ask this question
so
you know today kids who are born
today are born into a world where the
internet is always
on high quality internet streaming it's
always on the moment these kids are born
by the age of 6 to 8 months they start
using their iPads and whatnot and they
can navigate these operating systems
brilliantly the way older people can't
and they have been born into this world
of the internet so if you are a
youngster you you kind of would imagine
that the internet will last forever it's
you take it for granted it's always
there it's always been there but if you
just go back a couple of decades maybe
30 years you go back to the early 90s or
mid90s there was no internet anywhere I
think internet started appearing in
India in the in the second half of the
1990s and in the US in the first half of
the 1990s but it was still a very it was
still a an absolute Rarity before that
there was no internet to speak of now
what is the internet is the question the
internet essentially is a whole bunch of
computers that are connected to each
other and that communicate in real time
at the speed of light more or less the
speed of light and there are servers and
server farms and cloud storage servers
and all that which host a whole bunch of
data and they serve these pages and all
that to to the N View to the end user
and we interact with these servers and
then how the internet happens there's a
tremendous amount of data today stored
across the
world so what would it take to take out
the internet first of all if there is a
solar flare if there's a magnetic storm
that fries the Earth's circuits it'll
Wipe Out the internet
instantaneously so and that's something
that's going to
happen you know a solar sto a
geomagnetic storm like the what even EV
the carington event it's going to happen
maybe next year maybe next decade Maybe
Next Century but it's going to happen do
we have defenses against that I'm not
quite sure about that so that could take
out the internet all this stuff that we
create it's it could it may not last
forever it may be wiped out and then if
you
uh let's let's the so one of the pillars
that the internet depends on is the
servers
the second connection the second pillar
the internet depends on is the
connections between these servers and
these connections are through submarine
cables so if you see this map or the
submarine cable map these are the cables
that actually pipe the internet to
various parts of the world and these are
typically transpacific transatlantic
trans Indian Ocean Etc cables so for
example if you look the Indian Ocean
region you have all these cables it's
not a whole lot of cables and if
something happens to these cables entire
countries can lose access to the
internet so this is more about
connectivity but when it comes to the
storage of data and the storage of web
web pages it's all about the servers
that the data is stored on if something
happens to the servers the the data
disappears forever in case there are no
backups so the internet is a fragile
thing it depends on this new techn this
new set of technologies that we have
developed over the past few
decades and uh it may not last forever
what could possibly replace the internet
maybe the maybe the Stone Age I don't
know no the internet if it doesn't get
destroyed it's going to get
iteratively um more and more complex and
eventually see right now we have a lot
of video on the internet initially it
was just text and Pages then you had
images digital images then you had video
now you have high quality video 4K video
8K video live story live streaming video
and all that eventually you may
have virtual reality stuff and and
three-dimensional images and whatnot
stored in the internet eventually it may
become holographic um you can only
speculate so that could be the future of
the internet it would not it will not be
replaced it'll just become go on
becoming better and better and more and
more complicated with more and more
capabilities
okay a lot more questions are there but
I won't be able to take them today let
me take some questions from the live
chat and here's a question by Amisha was
Mars once like
Earth so if you look at Mars it's
smaller than our planet uh but it's like
a smaller
version of Earth the gravity is I don't
know what is is it quarter of what we
have here definitely
significantly less than what we
experience on Earth here but Mars is the
only planet apart from Earth and Venus
that exists in the so-called Goldilocks
zone around the sun which is the Zone
where water can exist in liquid form it
is close enough to the Sun that water
can exist in liquid form uh right now
there's almost no water on the surface
of Mars except at the polar regions
where you have these polar ice caps but
there seems to be a lot of water under
the soil of under the surface of Mars
and if you look at the
the Topography of Mars you will find lot
of drainage channels lot of can canyons
and so on which give you
evidence of water activity on the planet
in the past so about a billion years
before today there was water on Mars
there was a large quantity of liquid
flowing water on Mars there were oceans
there were Lakes there were Rivers there
were floods there were canons all all
that stuff caused by water so Mars was
once warm it had a much thicker
atmosphere spere and it had a very large
quantity of flowing water it may even
have had possibly life even though we
don't have actual evidence of it hard
evidence but definitely a possibility so
yes Mars was much once much more like
Earth than what it is today today it is
a frigid desolate planet with a thin
atmosphere and whatever water exists
there is solid it's ice in the past it
was warm just like Earth Earth it had
water body is just like what we have
today okay
um let's see what other questions do we
have um maheswari says if we achieve
light speed can
we travel through
time okay um see light speed can't be
achieved the laws of physics forbid it
just look at the very basic equ
equations of special
relativity and uh yeah you have time
dilation for sure which tells you that
if if something is traveling the speed
of light it won't experience time so and
but you also have U other relativistic
effects one of the effects is that your
mass increases with with velocity the
faster you go the ma more massive the
object becomes so let's say you have a
proton that's traveling at 0.999 times
the speed of light
its mass is going to be much more than a
than a proton sitting in a rest frame
compared to you and me the
Observer so if a proton were to actually
try and Achieve light speed it would
have to gain infinite Mass an infinite
Mass doesn't exist in the universe right
so U ACH achieving light speed is just
simply
impossible and but it is theoretically
possible to travel very large distances
faster than the speed of light if you
kind of cheat not really cheating if you
use an Einstein Rosen Bridge of Wormhole
which kind of is a shortcut through
space and time but wormal are
theoretical and we don't know if it's
possible to make
them um but yes if you can Traverse a
wormhole a traversable wormhole and
certain conditions are fulfilled then
time travel could actually end up
happening but you can't uh achieve light
light speed U tradition Al or
conventionally without using a wormhole
it's not possible and even if you're
traversing a wormhole you're actually
traversing it at less than the speed of
light but you can reach places in the
universe that are much further away than
you can travel if the speed of light at
the same amount of time so you may
actually be able to travel super
luminally if you can use a wormhole you
know the end result is a super luminal
travel and then depending on the on the
velocity of the two mouth of Wormhole
Wormhole compared to each other you may
actually end up traveling through time
so theoretically some things are
possible theoretically using wormholes
time travel seems to be
possible but not not
otherwise yeah so
relativistic relativistic mechanics is
an interesting branch of physics
relativity
itself okay Matrix says how do animals
like dogs and birds communicate within
their species do they understand signals
or languages from other species too you
know whales let's take the example of
whales whales are these gigantic animals
that live in the oceans they are animals
they mammals they breed they have lungs
they don't they don't have gills like
fish so they have whale songs and they
have lots of different vocalizations and
they
have essentially it's it's a language
and they use that the these
vocalizations to communicate with each
other at very large distances distances
of more than hundreds or even thousands
of kilometers because sound travels very
large distances in in water in the
oceans so Veals communicate through
vocalizations there's also body language
communication the same goes for dolphins
uh which also belong to uh a closely
related uh group of
animals so they communicate through
vocalization and Body Language birds
birds have bird songs and each bird song
is is taught by the parents to the
children somehow and every species has a
certain set of
vocalizations so the vocalizations that
for example uh a parakeet or a parrot
will do is different from that what a
pigan would do that and it's different
from what a crow would do but they all
have their own set of vocalizations that
are taught bird songs that are taught in
B in in vocalizations that are used to
communicate and also there there are
other displays body language displays
and all that so multiple means of
communicating uh vocalization is
definitely uh one of the important
components of communication for Birds
when it comes to
dogs well dogs are very familiar to us
right we know how dogs behave so dogs
also have body language the tail wags
and the various growls and Barks that
they that they do and all
that uh they yeah so they communicate
through vocal means through body
language and so on it's the same thing
for all
species uh even cats and all
now when it comes to their intelligence
level it's definitely not as much uh
they are not as intelligent as we are as
far as we know dogs cats
Etc uh whales Dolphins elephants may be
more intelligent than what we imagine
perhaps um and they certainly would
understand at least some signals from
other
species because at the end of the day
you live in an environment where you
you're not the only species so you have
to understand the other species and some
species may be your prey some species
may be the your Predators some species
may represent a threat for you you may
cooperate with some species so you have
if you want to cooperate you have to
communicate in some way so yes there is
cross species communication definitely
that happens through body language
through vocalization and through many
other
means
okay what other question do we have
let's take maybe one more question
question one more question
um fishball says how can I change my
mindset and personality completely and
become a completely different person a
person who is the hero of my own book
yeah for that you have to go through a
whole process it's it's not something
that will happen overnight you first
identify what traits currently exist in
you what traits you possessed possess
what characteristics what what
capabilities you have that you to
identify what you like what you don't
like what you want to change what you
want to retain and then you have to
identify where you want to go eventually
you know what you want to become what
kind of better version of yourself you
want to become and then you have to
practice new habits it all change
happens through small habits you start
new habits and consistently continue
them over a long period of time and
eventually you you do become a separate
person so it's all about it's all about
raising your standards and I've been
requested this multiple times to make a
video about raising one standards so you
can't do it in in a single video so I'm
going to be making a series of videos a
whole series next year about raising
your standards so yeah do watch it'll
come
soon okay Tas says what's the best
telescope for a beginner to get if
somebody wants to see Saturn why seeing
Mercury is hard by telescope can you
suggest some telescopes which are cost
effective you know I'm sorry I can't
help you with this I've never had a
telescope as a kid I always wanted to
have one but somehow or other I never
had one today I can certainly afford
telescopes but um I live in a city
that's very bright too too much light so
I don't know what's a good telescope
maybe I can look into it I will not do
it in real time right now um but yeah
what you would want to do is to go to
whichever is your favorite online store
that Amazon or whatever and look at
telescopes of various price ranges
whatever is within your budget and try
try and find the best telescope within
within that price range and how do you
find the best telescope see the star
ratings if it is above four 4.5 that's
it's great but obviously it should have
lots of reviews and then you should see
what their capabilities are can it
resolve Saturn can it resolve Jupiter
can it resolve Mercury and so on so
that's what you would do I personally
don't have any experience so I can't say
sorry about that why is it hard to see
Mercury by telescope because it's a very
small planet it's probably smaller than
our moon and it's so far away it's
really close to the Sun and you have to
be really careful you don't point a
telescope anywhere near the sun it will
destroy your eyes immediately so for
these reasons Mercury it's it's very
hard to see Mercury on a
telescope all right we have crossed two
hours 15 minutes I need to end the
session over here today um should I take
uh there are so many questions I won't
be able to take them I'm so sorry about
that Anisha says any tips for jenzi on
what skills to focus on in 2025 just
focus on what skills to focus
on well it depends on what kind of
career you want to have but overall the
skill you should focus on is how to
learn learning itself is a skill how to
learn new things how to learn things
that you are not exposed to and how to
learn those skills
quickly I think that's the in in today's
world in today's AI enabled world where
everything is changing so rapidly the
one skill everybody needs to have is how
to learn how to learn new skills
quickly and how to and the other thing
jenzi needs is focus and discipline so
learn how to be focused learn how to be
more disciplined because genzi compared
to other
Generations seems to be a little bit
lacking in these things so I would say
learn the skill you need to learn is how
to learn new skills secondly how to be
focused and thirdly how to be
disciplined and work hard all right all
right thank you everybody for all the
questions apologies to those of you
whose questions I could not take and
this is the end of the final live stream
the final episode of ask abijit for this
year next weekend the first episode of
next year will go live until then take
care and keep asking questions keep
raising your standards I'll see you soon
next week bye